Inventory of the Dorsey-Coupland Papers 1840-1876, 1843-1865
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1840-1866, n.d., 174 items. (Box-folder 1:1-4)
  - Sister of Edm. Ruffin [Jane S. Dupuy], at Windrow, to Mary [?], 4 March 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Bears ALS from Jane S. Dupuy, at Windrow, to Sister [?], n.p., 13 March 1863. Hopes that she is doing well now that she is "out of the reach of Lincoln's minions"; feels sad when she thinks of Anna and Mattie and "their confinement & the innumerable privations & annoyances they have had to endure & yet I wonder that they have not suffered more from such wretches"; is distressed that such a large area of the Confederacy is occupied by Union forces; feels that the Confederacy will gain independence but is sure that the war will last for years.
  - Carter [Coupland], Mobile, [Alabama] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 21 M[ar]ch 1863., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has been ill with a chill and a high fever but feels fine now; received a letter from Brother [John R. Coupland?] this morning and reports they had been sick after she left their house; informs her of the high prices in Mobile -- flour at $80 a barrel, turkeys at $6-7 each, beef from $0.50 to $0.75 a pound, and all else in proportion; has received letters from Jno. [John] Henly [sic] and Miles who especially wish to be remembered to her; will go up to see Mollie this evening.
  - Mattie [Pierce], Warrenton, James City County, Virginia, to Harriett Cary, Richmond, Virginia, 15 April 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Did not realize how much she loved her home until she was forced to leave it under "such trying circumstances"; describes her departure under shelling from Union troops; was very happy to see the Confederate troops on Saturday; mentions shaking hands with Col. Tabb and receiving an introduction to Col. Shinglar; informs her that one of her negroes has been arrested and others are "quite cool indeed to us"; fears that the Yankees will "fire the town when our men leave."
    Bears ALS from Mattie [Pierce], Warrenton, James City County, Virginia, to Harriett Cary, Richmond, Virginia, 18 April 1863. Received a visit from Mr. Hansford as they were about to retire but stayed up and talked with him; rode down to Uncle's, where they were cooking food to send to Richmond; Uncle wishes her to stay with them; saw four Confederate officers while there; has learned that General Wise has left "dear old W[illiam]sburg again in the Yankee hands"; met Tom Barlow and Johnie Maupin as they were going into town and learned later they made it into town; wishes she [HC] were with her so they could console one another.
  - Carter [Coupland], Mobile, [Alabama] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 21 M[ar]ch 1863., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Mattie [Pierce], Warrenton, James City County, Virginia, to Harriett Cary, Richmond, Virginia, 15 April 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Harriette [?], Centre Hill, Petersburg, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 21 April 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs her that she "left the Williamsburg captives well and doing as well as possible under the trying circumstances"; had left Mrs. Coupland's family as they were all improving from their illness; was shelled during General Wise's attack on the south side of the James River but little damage was done; has decided with her family "to remain till the last extremity, which I very much fear will not only be persecution but starvation"; gives details of the movements of General Wise and the situation of the war in her area.
  - John Coupland, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 26 April 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Left Willamsburg twelve days before after being ordered by General Wise to report to Richmond; still subject to conscription as he is not yet forty years old; was upset to leave his "dependent family in the hands of the Yankees... and at this particular time with dear Sue expected daily to be confined, and not a physician in the place"; his family and Ma [Henley]'s are dependent on his efforts to find something to keep them all from starving as the Yankees forbade the citizens from going to the mill for some weeks; describes the Yankees as "stringent" and "diabolical"; informs her that if the Yankees relinquish the Lunatic Asylum there is a need for officers there, and as he has secured a clerkship there he is exempt from military service; describes the shelling of Williamsburg; escaped injury from the shells even though they fell quite close to his house; will sell Mac for her as horses are high in price; advises that her hands Edmund and John should be sold as they will sell for $4,000 and the family has nothing to live on now.
  - Juliana [Coupland], n.p., to her father John R. Coupland, Richmond, Virginia, 28 April 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs him that Uncle William Hancock has heard that they "were crying for bread"; has been told that everything is in plenty at Richmond and that there are many people there as if there were no war going on; is sorry to tell him that the Yankees will not let them go out without taking the oath of allegiance in one fashion or another; was excited that he was to get an office in the Asylum but was very disappointed that the Yankees kept hold of it; tries to help Mother as much as possible; asks after her relatives; informs him of the birth of his son on the first of May that they named Carter.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, n.p., to John R. Coupland, Richmond, Virginia, 8 May 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Distressed to hear that he has to leave his family to serve in the military; hopes he can be stationed at the Asylum so as to be closer to his family; he is welcome to the money she sent; would like to send more money but she is barely scraping along on Carter's kindness; will send more money if he secures the clerkship in Richmond; encloses $50 and is sure Mr. Beechtrout [?] will take Confederate money.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Sue H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 13 May 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Expresses his sadness at having to be separated from her; asks after his children and gives instructions for their upbringing; is disappointed that the Yankees have not relinquished the Asylum, and so he is without an appointment there; will try to remain out of the Army and secure a clerkship for her sake; expresses his anxiety to serve, but "now that I am exempt I must see what can be done for our good"; is sure that the war will soon be over and will lead to "the establishment of our people among the nations of Earth as an independent republic"; describes the gloom cast over the South as a result of the death of [Stonewall] Jackson, for "He was a grand specimen of all that was great and good in human nature"; describes the funeral procession.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Sue H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 3 June 1863., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Shares in the joy of the birth of their new baby; wishes he could be with her to share the burden of keeping the family since she has no servants to assist her; intended to send her some Virginia money, but was told that "there was no passing below, and no goods to be purchased in Williamsburg"; asks her what currency she can use and he will convert all he can to send to her; has yet to secure a position of employment but expects one daily in the Department for the settlement of deceased soldiers' claims with a salary of $125 per month; board is $100 a month in Richmond, but will endeavor to live as cheaply as possible to send her the most money he can; describes the war as lasting "until children yet unborn shall grow to be men, and their children and children's children shall raise up in turn to demand the rights for which their fathers fought, unless our enemy in the meantime be overpowered, or, ashamed of his wickedness, shall award that justice he has so long withheld"; shares his faith in the people, army, and President of the Confederacy; describes the area surrounding Richmond as being quite beautiful; intends to visit the fort of James Semple; sends love to all, especially the children.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 19 July 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Thanks her for her letter; declares that "could Vicksburg have been succored in time, and Meade not been fortunate enough to have found a stronghold when driven before our irresistible army, 6 months would have found us in the enjoyment of Peace"; assures her that she need not worry about Mobile as he believes it will not be attacked; has not heard from anyone behind Yankee lines since last he wrote her; informs her that the Yankees have allowed the residents of Williamsburg to receive supplies, and that they are furnishing the needy in town with provisions; has learned that "Greenbacks" are worth about six times that of Confederate money; worries about his family's money problems, as they are in need of many things but have no money with which to buy them; thanks her for the shirts she and Carter sent, but cannot accept them as a gift; does not wish to take her money, but she is welcome to any of his that will be useful to her; will write brother Carter soon.
  - J[ohn] R. C[oupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Sue H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 26 July 1863., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Enclosed $50 southern money in his last letter which took $125 Confederate money to purchase, and the rates are going up sharply, it now taking $300 Confederate to purchase $100 State Bank; expects to procure some "Greenbacks" from a man who is coming from General Lee's army, as the Confederate soldiers take them from the pockets of dead Yankees; has heard that the Yankees have let Mr. Spear through to the front lines of Williamsburg with provisions and hopes that he brought her butter, vegetables, and fowl; suffers greatly at the thought of his wife and young children suffering; excuses her for not writing because he knows it is difficult for her to know who is going outside Williamsburg; hopes that she will be able to get out a letter soon; asks her to send a list of what she needs and cannot procure herself, and he will get the items for her; declares his faith that "Genl. Lee and his Army are invincible"; asks after his children; has sold Mac for $1200 and asks if she can use Virginia Treasury notes in Williamsburg.
  - John [R. Coupland], Huguenot Springs, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 16 Aug[ust] 1863., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Went to Huguenot Springs after suffering a headache and pain in the liver for two weeks; hopes to recover fully in a short time even though he is still suffering from bowel complaint that has "defied the kind attentions of both Cousin John [Dupuy] and Dr. W[alker]"; received the box she sent with the shirts she made him; informs her that he pays the least amount for board of any clerk in this area, being $70 a month while most rooms go for $100-$125 per month; tells her that $3 Confederate buys $1 of State Bank money and $10 of the same will buy $1 Yankee funds; hears that the Yankees are still allowing provisions into Williamsburg and that his family is well, though he has not yet had a letter from them; believes that his sickness results from "hard & hot marching around Richmond where the 20,000 Yankees at the White House threatened the city"; marched one night from 11 p.m. to daybreak, being 16 miles, and slept on the ground with no blankets.
  - [John R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to Sue [H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 19 Aug[ust] 1863., 10 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Understands that the only way she can get a letter out to him is if the content would not offend their enemies; advises her to write in a "plain, cold, business way" in order that it may be allowed to be sent; gives details of his sickness and convalescence at Huguenot Springs; assures her that he is strengthening daily, so not to worry; is upset that she cannot use the $50 State Bank money he sent her after paying $125 Confederate for it; could not procure Yankee money from the source he expected to; informs her that the exchange rate is $900 Confederate to $100 Yankee; asks her for a list of necessities so that he can procure them for her rather than try to convert his money to send to her; suggests that she sell whatever beef, fowls, etc., she can in order to raise money for the family; speaks of the letter Cousin John [Dupuy] received from Uncle Edmund Ruffin; informs her that Nannie Ruffin is dead, and Thomas, Cousin Ed's oldest son, was taken prisoner in Pennsylvania and has not been heard from since, and that the "old man [Cousin Ed]... says he desires to live long enough to see his country free, and then he would willingly die"; shares news of family and friends; asks after his children.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to Sue [H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 24 Aug[ust] 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has heard that camp fever is raging at Yorktown; advises her that if it reaches Williamsburg to pack up both her and Ma's family and go to the farm; describes his only consolation as writing to her and thereby feeling her presence with him; was able to hear Mr. Leyburn speak at Dr. Hoge's church; asks if it is possible that she sell things from the farm to Mr. Blassingham or some other shopkeeper and obtain the supplies he may have in his store; hopes that his newborn son is called Carter Harrison.
  - J[ohn R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia] to [Sue H. Coupland], [Williamsburg, Virginia], 27 Aug[ust] 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has received with joy the first letter she has written since they were separated; is distressed at the news that "that old scoundrel [Mr. Spear] should have failed, in the most brutal manner, to perform the only thing that comforted me with respect to your situation" in neglecting her in her time of need; hopes that he will be able to get them out of Williamsburg but cannot reveal his plans as yet; informs her that Molly Marshall has arrived in Virginia from Mobile, fearing that the enemy will take the city soon, and that Mother has gone up to Greensboro where General Cocke has offered her his nice place.
  - J[ohn] R. Coupland, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Carter Coupland], n.p., 7 Sept[ember] 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has put off writing to him till he could see Harriet; saw her at church and was told that Harriet has written both Mother and him and finds it strange that they have not received her letters; assures him that Harriet is quite well as she weighs 150 pounds and "looks better than anyone I have seen since the War commenced"; informs him of Mr. Spear's neglect, which has resulted in his [John's] family not having any flour or bacon in the house for weeks; fears for the citizens of Williamsburg, for "What with Yankee restrictions and scarcity of fuel, cold and starvation stares them in the face" once winter arrives; hopes to rent a cottage at Ashland where he can move his family; will make do with a plank bedstead and table if he cannot also bring up his furniture; discusses military matters and the movements of various generals.
  - Daniel Wheeler, Mobile, [Alabama] to Jane Dorsey, n.p., 7 Sept[ember 18]63., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Sends the $150 check from Messrs. Bull and Foster; hopes it reaches her safely.
  - [John R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Sue H. Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia], 15 Sept[ember] 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Asks her to apply to the Federal authorities to be allowed to leave Williamsburg and to bring whatever furniture and baggage she can; gives instructions for his plans for getting her out of the town.
  - Dr. J.J. Dupuy, (nephew of Edmund Ruffin), Assistant Surgeon, 15th Georgia Infantry, at the Confederate hospital at Huguenot Springs, to his aunt, [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 22 Sept[ember] 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Thanks her for her letter of the 1st; describes Cousin John [R. Coupland]'s visit to the Huguenot Springs and the cheer which he brought by his presence; knows that John is attempting to secure a home on the railroad, and Dr. Walker has been trying to find one, but without success; visited Nattoway recently and saw all the family; mentions that all are well, except Julia who still suffers from headaches.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], Greensboro, to John [R. Coupland], n.p., 23 Sept[ember] 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Suggests that he make inquiries of Mr. Saunders about securing a cottage for his family in the village where they now reside if his plans cannot be carried out; also suggests going to Danville to see Dr. Th[om]as Atkinson, who was his doctor at the Springs, about relocating his family to that town; would greatly prefer the family to come to Greensboro with her to stay at General Cocke's place, where she and Carter could take care of them.
  - John [R. Coupland], Richmond, [Virginia], to Mrs. John R. [Sue H.] Coupland, Williamsburg, Virginia, 1 Oct[ober] 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has learned from Col. Dupuy that it would be possible for her to be allowed to leave Williamsburg once proper application is made to the authorities, encourages her to take this step so that she is able to leave Williamsburg; warns her that though Mr. Darlington is supplying her with provisions, it is certainly possible that her source may unexpectedly cease and leave her in the same position she was in just a few weeks ago; has secured a cottage in Ashland about eighteen miles from Richmond for his family; mentions the offer of living with his mother at the place of General Cocke; gives her the option of choosing where she wants to live but would rather she move to the Ashland cottage; will give this letter to Col. D[upuy] who will make application for her if she decides to leave.
  - Carter [Coupland], Greensboro, to [John R. Coupland], n.p., 11 Oct[ober] 1863., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Is recuperating from having typhoid fever while in Mobile; wishes he could relieve the suffering of his [JRC's] young children; strongly urges him to remove his family from Williamsburg; sends his love to Jno. [John] Henly [sic] and to Miles; informs him that Mother is healthy and that Tiff and the children are well.
    Bears ALS from J[uliana] Dorsey to John [R. Coupland], n.d. Was able to meet a man at church who will take a box to Richmond; will send the box in care of John Henly [sic] as she has learned that he [JRC] has gone to retrieve his family from Williamsburg; wishes him great success; hopes that Sue will write as soon as she is settled in her new home in Ashland; informs him that she will pay for a servant because he needs one, and that he also needs a girl; asks for his and his children's measure for shoes so that she can get some for him; is knitting him two flannel shirts; sends one shirt and six handkerchiefs. 1 p.
  - Jane [S. Dupuy], Prince Edward [County], to her sister, [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 23 Oct[ober] 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Wishes they were together for mutual solace and consolation; worries greatly about William as his regiment has been heavily engaged and she has not yet heard from him; mentions the box sent by John M. to Mary that was robbed of everything but two tins of sardines and four cakes of soap; informs her that the tea set she [JSD] had deposited in Richmond for safekeeping has been robbed of every cup and saucer; describes the family with whom she is living; sends her love to sister's family.
  - Carter [Coupland], on board Steamer Senator, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 8 Nov[ember] 1863., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Is on his way to Selma with 450 troops; has no right to complain since he is doing well, but is "sick & tired of the life I am leading!" and knows there are better days in store for him; worries about Harriett and her "dependent situation" and wishes he could be her protector; thanks her for the warm shirts she made him.
  - Carter Coupland, on board Steamer Reindeer, at Selma, Alabama, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 24 Nov[ember] 1863., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Received her letter of the 12th, but has no time to respond to it; informs her that Capt. Baldwin has sold the Senator and that the Reindeer is one of the nicest boats on the river; mentions that John Marshall is at Mrs. Sayre's recovering after being severely wounded.
  - Molly Marshall, Mobile, [Alabama], to her aunt, [Juliana Dorsey?], n.p., 30 Nov[ember] 1863., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Had not expected to have to return to Mobile but was forced to after her husband John [Marshall] was severely wounded; realizes the probability of his never recovering the use of his arm; gives details of John's wounding and how the Yankees wanted to take him prisoner, but the ladies would not allow that since it appeared as though he were to die at any moment; describes the fuss being made over him at Mrs. Sayre's; asks whether it is time to plant and what should be planted.
  - Char[le]s L. C. Dupuy, at Paroled Camp, 1st Louisiana Regiment Artillery, near Enterprise, to Juliana [Dorsey], n.p., 21 Dec[embe]r 1863., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Had attempted to make the acquaintance of Dr. Ruffin when he [CLCD] had returned to Demopolis from Greensboro, but Dr. Ruffin had not been home; is sorry to hear of the death of one of Mr. Witherspoon's children; had arrived "like a 'bomb-shell'" at Nottoway at daybreak as no one was expecting his arrival; escorted Annie and Cousin Jane to Cousin Emily H. Dupuy's home in Prince Edward to spend the winter; had met John Copeland [sic] in Richmond and was quite glad to hear his family was out of Williamsburg and in Richmond; expects to be ordered to Mobile for duty soon.
  - Major Edw[ard] B. Smith, assistant to the Chief of Ordnance, War Department, Ordnance Bureau, [C.S.A.], Richmond, [Virginia], to Mattie Pierce, n.p., 23 Jan[uar]y 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Informs her that the examination for arithmetic for clerkships in that bureau is to be held in Room 18 of the War Department at 1 p.m. on the following Monday.
  - [Molly Marshall], Cottage Farm, to her aunt [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 4 Feb[ruary] 1864., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Shares her despair over her husband's [John] maiming in the war; he is still very much in pain and goes to Dr. Mordecai once a week, but the doctor cannot give them hope for full recovery either; is grateful to the help their neighbor Mr. S. has provided; felt it best to have their own home while John recovered as his mind was so disturbed while at Mrs. Sayre's; has purchased a buggy to carry John to and from his company, which is stationed three miles away; expects Cousin John Dupuy and his sister-in-law to arrive that day; reminds her that Cousin Asa Dupuy was beaten so badly by the Yankees that he died; shares news of friends and family.
  - Jane [S. Dupuy], Prince Edward [County], to her sister [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 24 Feb[ruary] 1864., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)